Osborne Family Papers
Osborne Family Papers
Osborne Family (A) - John Hall Osborne and offspring
Osborne Family (B) - Thomas Mott Osborne and offspring
Coffin family
Devens family
Garrison family
Harris family
Mott family
Pelham family
Storrow family
Wright family
Yarnall family
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Osborne Family Papers consist of correspondence and private records of the Osborne family and related branches of the Coffin, Devens, Garrison, Harris, Mott, Pelham, Storrow, Wright and Yarnall families. The bulk dates of the papers are 1812-1968, with a concentration in the period 1880-1925. Auburn, New York, has been the Osborne family home since the early nineteenth century. Relatives whose correspondence is well represented among the papers also resided in Boston, Cambridge, and Springfield, Mass., and Philadelphia, Penn. Genealogical charts have been prepared (see end of Biographical History section); while they are not meant to be comprehensive, the charts will assist in identifying members who figure prominently in the correspondence.
The major contributor to the collection was Thomas Mott Osborne. He accumulated approximately half the papers in the course of a career in business, education, politics and penology. Other contributors include Peter Pelham, frontier army officer, David Wright, New York lawyer, David Munson Osborne, manufacturer of harvesting machinery, and Lithgow Osborne, diplomat, conservationist and foundation executive.
There are in excess of 150,000 letters, telegrams and postcards; with few exceptions the letters are arranged in chronological order. Correspondents include authors, bankers, businessmen, U.S. cabinet officers, churchmen, civil service employees, congressmen, convicts, diplomats (both American and European), educators, state governors, inventors, journalists, lawyers, musicians, politicians, publishers, U.S. presidents, reformers of every stripe and students. Particularly noteworthy are 80 letters from Franklin Delano Roosevelt (1910 to 1932) not counting those of his wife Eleanor; several hundred from Secretary of the Navy Josephus Daniels (1917 to 1920); Katrina Trask, who endowed Yaddo, a writers' colony in Saratoga Springs; Attorney General Charles Devens (1873 to 1891); and tens and scores from Lucretia Coffin Mott (1835 to 1875), George Foster Peabody (1903 to 1926), Christian A. Herter (1923 to 1966), Louis M. Howe (1912 to 1924), German General Ludwig Klipfel (1890 to 1915), Herbert H. Lehman (1901- 1963), Gerrit Smith Miller (1898 to 1926), Alfred E. Smith (1918 to 1928), Oswald Garrison Villard (1896 to 1913); a handful from frontier generals Henry Atkinson and Henry Leavenworth (1812 to 1822); and one by Supreme Court Justice Oliver Wendell Holmes (1926).
Non-correspondence materials include account books, diaries and journals, institutional files, legal documents, photographs, speeches and the manuscript versions of published and unpublished writings. The papers comprise a range of subjects; among them, manufacturing, anti-imperialism, abolition, the social life and customs of Auburn, N.Y., the Auburn Barge Canal Project, Auburn Prison, campaign literature on the local, state and national levels, capital punishment, Cayuga County social life and customs, the Civil War, the Colorado State Penitentiary, conservation, convict labor, Creek Indians, crime and criminals, the Declaration of Atlantic Unity, the Democratic Party, disarmament, diplomacy, World War I, frontier and pioneer life in the American South and West, the George Junior Republic, gold mining in California, Harvard University, the International Harvester Trust Company, lawyers, the League of Nations, municipal government, music, the Mutual Welfare League, NATO, Norway and Norwegians, D.M. Osborne & Company, paroles and pardons, the Philippine Islands, Portsmouth Naval Prison, N.H., the Prison Association of New York, prisoners of war, probation, the Public Service Commission of New York, sawmills, Sing Sing Prison, Tammany Hall, temperance, travel, UNRRA, the U.S. Army, the War of 1812, Wells College, women's rights, and the Woodrow Wilson Foundation.
To guard against disorientation in a collection of this scope, the materials have been organized into five major groups, then subdivided by type of document or subject. Within the various sections items are organized either chronologically or under proper names which are alphabetically arranged. The five groups are: (I) Communications & Writings, (II) Organization Records, (III) Financial Papers, (IV) Legal Records, and (V) Memorabilia. The major groups and their subdivisions are as follows:
I. Communications and writings
A. Correspondence
B. Speeches
C. Writings
II. Organization records
A. General
B. Prisons
III. Financial records
A. Corporate
B. Personal
IV. Legal records
A. General
B. Suits
V. Memorabilia
A. General
B. Genealogies
C. Photographs
Individual folders in the collection are fully labeled, beginning with the collection name followed by the category/ies and if applicable the names of individuals or organizations and the inclusive dates. For example:
Osborne Family Papers > Communications and writings > Correspondence > Smith, John 1877-1883
Osborne Family Papers > Financial records > Record book > D.M. Osborne & Co. Board of directors minutes 1875-1912
I. Communications and writings
A wide range of materials is located within this group: correspondence, speeches and sermons, diaries, journals and a number of writings prepared for publication or entertainment.
A. Correspondence
Letters, telegrams and postcards are arranged in chronological order, down to the month (Boxes 1-205). The correspondence opens in 1812 and closes in 1968. There are few gaps of more than one month's duration after 1842, and the correspondence is particularly heavy between 1880 and 1925.
Incoming and outgoing correspondence is interfiled. Carbon copies of business correspondence are often stapled to the incoming letter to which they explicitly refer whenever the dates of incoming and outgoing business correspondence are less than thirty days apart. Thus, the carbon of an outgoing letter by Thomas Mott Osborne, dated 1907 Apr 27, is attached to the incoming letter sent by G.S. Pierson, dated 1907 Apr 23.
Letters which could be dated down to the year, but not the month, are located in a "General" folder, which precedes the monthly folders of a given year. Correspondence which cannot be dated is arranged alphabetically under the name of the sender (Boxes 206-207). A folder of unidentified correspondence is included in Box 207.
There are eighteen letter books of outgoing correspondence by Thomas Mott Osborne (Boxes 208-225). All are carbon copies or roller letter impressions on lightweight paper. The first fifteen volumes comprise the business and personal correspondence of. Osborne between 1892 and 1906. The remaining letter- books contain his correspondence (1898-1900) as a trustee of the George Junior Republic in Freeville, N.Y. Each letter- book contains its index of correspondents.
The last box of correspondence (Box 226) holds transcriptions of letters sent home by William Morris Davis during a world tour. He was a companion of Thomas Mott Osborne during their travels in 1877-1878.
The genealogical charts (see end of Biographical History section above) may be of assistance in identifying correspondents of all periods. The names of principals who figure in the correspondence are written in upper case letters. Birth, death and marriage dates have been provided whenever available, as well as nicknames and initials of correspondents who signed in the familiar form. A complete list of initials and nicknames is available at the repository. A card index, which was maintained by Thomas Mott Osborne and Lithgow Osborne, is available in Box 323. From it may be obtained the names and addresses of recurring correspondents and, occasionally, notes on the business conducted between these correspondents and the Osborne family.
B. Speeches
These papers (Boxes 227-232) include notes, drafts, typescripts and printed. speeches delivered by Thomas Mott Osborne, Lithgow Osborne, and others, mainly within the period 18951945. There is also a reminiscence delivered by David Wright in the 1880's on farming in Pennsylvania during the 1820's. The materials are arranged under the names of speakers, in alphabetical order, then by title or general subject, also alphabetically arranged. New York politics and prison reform are the recurring topics.
C. Writings
Within this section (Boxes 232-254) are gathered the writings of several members of the family. Items include articles and essays, books (both fiction and non-fiction, whether published or unpublished), editorials, diaries, film scripts, journals, notes, plays, reminiscences, reviews, short stories, travelogs and verse. The materials are arranged alphabetically, first under authors' names, next by type of material, and finally by title or subject. The major contributors are Agnes Devens Osborne, David Munson Osborne, Eliza Wright Osborne, Lithgow Osborne, Thomas Mott Osborne -- all of whom have diaries here -- and various inmates of Auburn, Portsmouth, and Sing Sing prisons.
A substantial part of this section is taken up by the writings of Thomas Mott Osborne. The materials are in draft and printed form. Among his published works found here in various stages of draft are the articles and essays "Prison efficiency" (1915), "The prison of the future" (1917), and "Prison reform" (1915); a serial narrative, "The tale of a green duck on the Susquehanna" (1910), a discursive essay which sometimes dips into New York politics and newspaper wars; the script for the film "The right way" (1921); and three books, Within Prison Walls (1913), Society and Prisons (1916), and the second half of Prisons and Common Sense (1924). There are several unpublished articles, film scripts, and plays, as well as chapter drafts of a book, variously titled "Reforming Sing Sing" and "Politics and Prisons." Near completion at the time of his death in 1926, the latter is an extended narrative and defense of his tenure as warden of Sing Sing Prison.
There are several diaries and journals. The diaries include those of Agnes Devens Osborne (1882-1895), David Munson Osborne (1839-1856), Eliza Wright Osborne (1867-1894), Jane Abbey Osborne (1884), David Wright (1843), William Pelham Wright (1862-1863), and an unidentified businessman of New York City (1846). The two vest pocket diaries of William Pelham Wright record his experiences as an artillery lieutenant from the Peninsular Campaign to Gettysburg, where he was wounded.
Journals are here distinguished from diaries in that they are often transcribed, do not form units coinciding with the beginning and end of the calendar year, and focus on a special activity or theme. The writing may range over many topics, but the theme continually reverts to a central occupation, such as travel or diplomacy, and the journal closes with the termination of that activity. The travel journals were written by Eliza Wright Osborne and another unidentified member of the family on trips through the American West between 1871 and 1880; by Thomas Mott Osborne on European, Caribbean, and world tours (1877-1884); and by Lithgow Osborne on journeys to Australia and Norway (1944-1946). There is also a 63-page journal by David Munson Osborne II, on leaving Paris for the United States in August and September of 1939. Some journals cover a shorter period, such as that of David Wright for March, 1828. The most extended are those of Thomas Mott Osborne as head of D.M. Osborne Company (1891-1896), and Lithgow Osborne (191417), first as personal secretary to Ambassador James W. Gerard, and later as third secretary of the American Embassy in Berlin. The journal of Lithgow Osborne includes incoming and outgoing letters which supplement his day-to-day reporting of embassy activity between 1914 and 1917.
Other works in the writings section include the galley proof of There is No Truce (1935), a biography of Thomas Mott Osborne by Rudolph W. Chamberlain; essays by convicts in Auburn and. Sing Sing prisons; an eyewitness account of the San Francisco earthquake and fire (1906); the MGM film script for Osborne of Sing Sing (1939); annotated scripts used by the Hasty Pudding Club at Harvard (1883-1884); articles on prison life and penal systems by a number of reformers and convicts; and miscellaneous compositions by members of the Osborne family.
II. Organization records
All government, fraternal, social and institutional records, are located within this group. The materials include agendas, constitutions and by-laws, directives, membership lists, memoranda, minutes, reports, printed materials and scrapbooks. The records of prisons and prison societies are filed separately at the end of this group.
A. General
All government, fraternal, social and institutional records, other than prison records, are located in this section (Boxes 254-267). The papers are filed alphabetically under the names of organizations, then alphabetically by type of record. Within folders items are filed in chronological order.
Among the papers are records of federal, state and municipal agencies of government. There are special orders and memoranda exchanged between the U.S. War Office and Capt. Peter Pelham between 1814 and 1822. The subjects relate to Indian affairs, stolen slaves, army recruiting and frontier settlement from St. Augustine, Fla., to the Upper Mississippi in the present Wisconsin. Diplomatic papers are filed. under the heading, U.S. Department of State. All were collected by Lithgow Osborne, who served in American embassies and legations in Berlin (1914-1917), Havana (1917), Copenhagen (1917-1919) and Oslo (1944-1946). Other papers in this category relate to his service with the American Peace Commission in Paris (1919), the Arms Limitation Conference in Washington (19211922), the Office of Strategic Services (1942-1944), the Atlantic Council of the United States (1955-1967) and the Declaration of Atlantic Unity (1956-1967). Of the diplomatic papers in this collection, the largest single gathering derives from Mr. Osborne's work in Berlin during the First World War. The records include copies of dispatches, memoranda of conversation with German officials (some in the German language) and reports on conditions in prisoner-of-war camps. As with other organization records, these papers are supplemented by letters in the correspondence section, journals in the writings section, miscellaneous items in the financial records group and photographs located under memorabilia.
New York State records were accumulated by Thomas Mott Osborne and his son, Lithgow. They served in elected and appointed office between 1903 and 1942. Among the papers are records of the state commissions on crime, prisons, and public utilities, the departments of conservation and correction, and the New York National Guard.
There is an extensive file which chronicles municipal government in Auburn, N.Y., where David Munson Osborne, Thomas Mott Osborne and Charles Devens Osborne -- father, son and grandson -- were elected to the office of mayor. The topics include charter revision, police and fire protection, municipal finance, street railways and the water board.
Among the political, social, fraternal, charitable and educational institutions represented are the American-Scandinavian Foundation, the Auburn Beethoven Club, the Committee to Defend America by Aiding the Allies, the George Junior Republic, for which there is an extensive file between 1896 and 1932, the League of Nations Non-Partisan Committee, the National Conference of Social Work, the Osborne School, Wells College in central New York, the Women's Educational and Industrial Union of Auburn, and the Yaddo reservation at Saratoga Springs, N.Y.
B. Prisons
The records of Auburn and Sing Sing prisons, and those of the Portsmouth Naval Prison constitute the bulk of this section (Boxes 268-278). Privately instituted and supported prison reform societies are also located in this section, among them, the Mutual Welfare League, the National Committee on Prisons, the Prison Association of New York, and the Prison Discipline Society. There are several reports prepared by the National Society of Prison Information on conditions in major prisons of the United States between 1920 and 1925.
III. Financial records
The financial papers are divided between corporate and private records, The materials are arranged in alphabetical order under the name of a person or company, then by type of record. Items include audits, bills and receipts, insurance policies, inventories, ledgers, minutes of board meetings, stock certificates, trust accounts and wage books. Loose materials are arranged chronologically within folders.
A. Corporate
The several firms represented in this section (Boxes 278284) include the Auburn Iron Company, the Auburn National Bank, the Auburn Publishing Company, the Auburn Savings Bank, the Buffalo Transparent Products Company, the Ellis Adding-Typewriting Company, D.M. Osborne & Company and the Osborne Hotel. The larger part of the records date from the period 1890-1910, with a handful of earlier records, such as the executive minutes of the Steam Saw-Mill Association, Manhattan Island (1824-1825), the accounts of Capt. Peter Pelham (1806-1826) and the receipt book of New York building contractor Ferris Pell (1824-1827). There is also a fine broadside, in color and dating from about 1875, which illustrates a variety of binders and reapers sold by D.M. Osborne & Company.
B. Personal
The family members whose financial papers appear in quantity include Thomas Mott Osborne, Lithgow Osborne and David Munson Osborne (Boxes 284- 294).
IV. Legal records
Legal records (Boxes 294-299) are arranged in alphabetical order under individual or corporate names then by type of document, also arranged alphabetically. Items include affidavits, contracts, deeds dating from 1808, guardianship papers from the eighteenth century, leases, mortgages, patents and wills of the Osborne family and the clients of David Wright. Court suits (Boxes 300-314) are filed together at the end of this group.
A. General
Many of the legal papers come from the files of David Wright and pertain to the sale of patents for farm machinery. Wright was on retainer for inventor William A. Kirby and businessman David Munson Osborne as their firm moved to the front rank in manufacturing. Several documents trace real estate transactions of the Osborne and Wright families in Cayuga County, N.Y. Among the corporate bodies represented here are the Auburn Gas Company, the Dolphin Point Association, the East Genesee Street and Seward Avenue Railway, the George Junior Republic, the Lake Ontario, Auburn & New York Railroad, the Lehigh Valley Railroad, the New York, West Shore & Buffalo Railway, the New York Telephone Company, the Lippincott Publishing Company and the Owasco Valley Oil Company. Among the curiosities are a draft petition (ca. 1843) addressed to the New York State Legislature from a county Temperance Society, the indenture for an apprentice cordwainer in Massachusetts (1794), a will dating from 1778, a plan of Silas Kirby's land in Dartmouth, N.H. (1786), warrants for school taxes (1822), a deed of New York City property signed by Thomas Ludlow Ogden (1824), a sharecropping agreement in Putnam County, Fla. (1878) and miscellaneous papers on real estate holdings of the Swan family (1809-1842).
B. Suits
Court suits are arranged alphabetically under the name of a case, expressed as Plaintiff v. Defendant. There is a complete trial record of New York v. Osborne, with supporting documents for the defense. There are also several affidavits, briefs and trial transcripts for litigation pleaded by David Wright in behalf of David Munson Osborne. Patent rights were generally at issue in these cases.
V. Memorabilia
Memorabilia are divided into three sections: general; genealogies; and photographs. The materials, which include non-manuscript items such as engraving plates and phonodiscs are organized under individuals' names, alphabetically arranged, then subdivided by type.
A. General
This section (Boxes 315-344) contains papers and objects derived almost exclusively from the main branch of the Osborne family. Among the items are address books, appointment books, biographical data, book orders, commissions to appointive office, diplomas, guest lists, invitations, itineraries, medals, membership cards, newspaper clippings, notebooks, obituaries, political ephemera, school records, scrapbooks, transcripts of interviews and visas. One notable item is the scrapbook maintained by Lithgow Osborne during his years in the American Embassy in Berlin (1914- 1917). In it are notes and letters from Walter Hines Page, James W. Gerard and Robert Lansing.
B. Genealogies
The genealogies (Boxes 344-346) trace the lineage of the Osborne family and related branches back to the seventeenth century. The materials are organized under the name of family heads and include notes, charts and searches, both bound and unbound. Several family trees are also available (see Biographical History section, above).
C. Photographs
There is an extensive collection of unmounted photographs (Boxes 346-358). As with the assortment of general memorabilia, the photographs are mostly of the Auburn branch of the Osborne family. Other subjects include the George Junior Republic, Sing Sing Prison, agricultural machinery, travel in. Europe and the Carribean and German prisoner-of-war camps during World War I. There are autographed photos of Lucretia Coffin Mott and Charles Evans Hughes Nine albums and one box of glass negatives are located at the end of this section.
Bound volumes and oversize materials
Bound volumes, such as notebooks, published works and ledgers, are numbered consecutively throughout the collection and recapitulated at the end of the Shelf List. Oversized items, also numbered consecutively at the end of the Shelf List, are situated at the end of the boxed collection. Dummy folders for the oversized packages have been placed among the boxed papers.
Arrangement of the Collection
See Scope and Contents above.
Other Related Finding Aids
Several additional lists are available in the finding aids file, including:
A partial list of names, businesses, and subjects by year
A list of Lucretia Coffin Mott correspondence
Recapitulation of oversize packages and their contents
Recapitulation of bound volumes and their contents
Subject and Genre Headings